I have all my life wondered what "mind-boggling" meant.
لقد تساءلت طوال حياتي عن ماذا يعني محيرة العقل.
After two days here, I declare myself boggled, and enormously impressed,
بعد يومين هنا، أعلن نفسي متحير، ومعجب بشدة،
and feel that you are one of the great hopes --
وأشعر أنكم أحد الآمال الكبيرة.
not just for American achievement in science and technology,
ليس فقط للإنجاز الأمريكي في العلوم والتكنلوجيا،
but for the whole world.
لكن لكل العالم.
I've come, however, on a special mission on behalf of my constituency,
لكن ، لقد توصلت، في مهمة خاصة نيابة عن دائرتي الإنتخابية.
which are the 10-to-the-18th-power -- that's a million trillion --
التي هي 10 أس 18 -- الرقم مليون تريلليون --
insects and other small creatures, and to make a plea for them.
حشرات وكائنات صغيرة أخرى، وأن أقوم بمرافعة نيابة عنهم.
If we were to wipe out insects alone, just that group alone, on this planet --
إذا كنا سنقضي على الحشرات وحدها، فقط تلك المجموعة، على الكوكب--
which we are trying hard to do --
الذي نحاول فعله بشدة--
the rest of life and humanity with it would mostly disappear from the land.
فان بقية الحياة ومعها الإنسانية ستختفي من الأرض.
And within a few months.
وخلال أشهر قليلة.
Now, how did I come to this particular position of advocacy?
الآن، كيف توصلت لهذا الوضع الخاص من الدفاع؟
As a little boy, and through my teenage years,
كطفل صغير، وخلال فترة مراهقتي،
I became increasingly fascinated by the diversity of life.
أصبحت مفتوناً بإضطراد بتنوع الحياة.
I had a butterfly period, a snake period, a bird period, a fish period, a cave period
قضيت فترة الفراشة، فترة الثعبان، فترة الطائر، فترة السمكة، وفترة الكهف
and finally and definitively, an ant period.
وفي النهاية وبالتأكيد، فترة النملة.
By my college years, I was a devoted myrmecologist,
وبحلول وقت الكلية، كنت مكرساً لدراسة الأحياء،
a specialist on the biology of ants,
ومتخصص في علم أحياء النمل.
but my attention and research continued to make journeys
لكن إنتباهي وبحوثي تواصلت لتصبح رحلات
across the great variety of life on Earth in general --
عبر التنوع العظيم للحياة في كوكب الأرض عامة.
including all that it means to us as a species, how little we understand it
وتشمل كل ما تعنيه لنا كمخلوقات، الكم القليل الذي نفهمه عنها
and how pressing a danger that our activities have created for it.
وكيف أن الضغط يشكل خطراً بالأنشطة التي صنعناها لها.
Out of that broader study has emerged a concern and an ambition,
خارج دراستنا الواسعة تطور قلق وتخوّف،
crystallized in the wish that I'm about to make to you.
تبلور في الأمنية التي سأطلبها منكم.
My choice is the culmination of a lifetime commitment
خياري هو تتويج لإلتزام مدى الحياة
that began with growing up on the Gulf Coast of Alabama, on the Florida peninsula.
الذي بدأ في النمو في خليج ساحل ألاباما، في شبه جزيرة فلوريدا.
As far back as I can remember, I was enchanted by the natural beauty of that region
يعود تاريخها حسب ما أتذكره، كنت مسحوراً بالجمال الطبيعي لتلك المنطقة
and the almost tropical exuberance of the plants and animals that grow there.
والوفرة شبه الاستوائية من الحيوانات و النباتات التي تنمو هناك.
One day when I was only seven years old and fishing,
يوم ما عندما كنت في السابعة من العمر أصطاد،
I pulled a "pinfish," they're called, with sharp dorsal spines, up too hard and fast,
أصطدت سمكة دبوس -- تسمى هكذا، مع زعانفها الظهرية الحادة-- الصعبة جداً والسريعة.
and I blinded myself in one eye.
وسببت العمى لأحدى عيني.
I later discovered I was also hard of hearing,
وأكتشفت لاحقاً أنني عانيت من صعوبة السمع،
possibly congenitally, in the upper registers.
ربما بالفطرة، في السجلات العلوية.
So in planning to be a professional naturalist --
لذا في التخطيط لأن أصبح محترف طبيعة--
I never considered anything else in my entire life --
لم أفكر بتاتاً في أي شئ طوال حياتي--
I found that I was lousy at bird watching and couldn't track frog calls either.
وجدت أنني كنت قمئ في مشاهدة الطيور وكذلك لم أستطع ترقب نداء الضفدع.
So I turned to the teeming small creatures
لذا فقد تحولت الى المخلوقات الصغيرة
that can be held between the thumb and forefinger:
التي يمكن حملها بين الأصبعين الإبهام و السبابة:
the little things that compose the foundation of our ecosystems,
الأشياء الصغيرة التي تؤلف نظم أنظمتنا الحيوية.
the little things, as I like to say, who run the world.
الأشياء الصغيرة، أرغب بالقول ، التي تدير العالم.
In so doing, I reached a frontier of biology so strange, so rich,
وفي القيام بذلك، توصلت الى حدود غريبة للأحياء، غنية للغاية
that it seemed as though it exists on another planet.
التي بدت كما لو أنها موجودة على كوكب آخر.
In fact, we live on a mostly unexplored planet.
في الواقع، نحن نعيش في عالم غير مكتشف تقريباً.
The great majority of organisms on Earth remain unknown to science.
الأغلبية العظمى من الكائنات الحية لا تزال غير معروفة للعلم.
In the last 30 years, thanks to explorations in remote parts of the world
في ال 30 سنة الأخيرة، بفضل الإكتشافات في الأماكن البعيدة من العالم
and advances in technology,
وتقدم التكنلوجيا،
biologists have, for example, added a full one-third of the known frog and other amphibian species,
حصل علماء الاحياء، كمثال، أضافوا ثلث الضفادع المعروفة وغيرها من البرمائيات الأخرى،
to bring the current total to 5,400,
لجلب المجموع الكلي الحالي الى 5400.
and more continue to pour in.
ويتواصل ضخ المزيد.
Two new kinds of whales have been discovered, along with two new antelopes,
نوعان جديدان من الحيتان تم إكتشافهم، بجانب أثنين من الظباء،
dozens of monkey species and a new kind of elephant --
كميات من القرود ونوع جديد من الأفيال.
and even a distinct kind of gorilla.
وحتى نوع فريد من الغوريلا!
At the extreme opposite end of the size scale, the class of marine bacteria,
وفي مقابلة كبيرة في الحجم، فان صنف البكتريا البحرية،
the Prochlorococci -- that will be on the final exam --
البروتشلوروكوكي -- التي ستكون في الإختبار النهائي--
although discovered only in 1988, are now recognized as likely the most abundant organisms on Earth,
رغماً عن أنها أكتشفت فقط عام 1988، فانها معروفة الآن كأرجح أكثر الكائنات وفرة على الأرض.
and moreover, responsible for a large part of the photosynthesis that occurs in the ocean.
وعلاوة على ذلك، مسئولة من جزء كبير من عملية التمثيل الضوئي التي تحدث في المحيطات.
These bacteria were not uncovered sooner
هذه البكتريا لم تكتشف عاجلاً
because they are also among the smallest of all Earth's organisms --
لأنها تقريباً من بين أصغر الكائنات في الأرض--
so minute that they cannot be seen with conventional optical microscopy.
حتى اللحظة لا يمكن رؤيتها بالمجهر البصري التقليدي.
Yet life in the sea may depend on these tiny creatures.
لكن الحياة في المحيطات ربما تعتمد على هذه الكائنات الصغيرة.
These examples are just the first glimpse of our ignorance of life on this planet.
هذه الأمثلة هي فقط مجرد لمحة لجهلنا بالحياة على هذا الكوكب.
Consider the fungi -- including mushrooms, rusts, molds and many disease-causing organisms.
بالنظر الى الفطريات-- ضمنها المشروم، الصدأ، العفن والعديد من الكائنات التي تسبب الأمراض.
60,000 species are known to science,
60 ألف كائن معروفة للأوساط العلمية،
but more than 1.5 million have been estimated to exist.
لكن ما يزيد على مليون ونصف يُقدّر أنهم موجودين.
Consider the nematode roundworm, the most abundant of all animals.
بالنظر الى الدودة الخيطية، الأكثر وفرة بين جميع الكائنات.
Four out of five animals on Earth are nematode worms --
أربعة من كل خمسة من الحيوانات على الأرض هي دودة خيطية--
if all solid materials except nematode worms were to be eliminated,
إذا كان لابد من التخلص من جميع المواد الصلبة عدا الديدان الخيطية
you could still see the ghostly outline of most of it in nematode worms.
ما يزال يمكنكم رؤية المخطط الشبحي للديدان الخيطية.
About 16,000 species of nematode worms
حوالي 16 ألف كائن من الديدان الخيطية
have been discovered and diagnosed by scientists;
تم إكتشافها وتشخيصها بواسطة العلماء.
there could be hundreds of thousands of them, even millions, still unknown.
قد يكون هناك مئات الآلاف منها، ملايين حتى، ما يزال مجهولاً.
This vast domain of hidden biodiversity is increased still further
هذا المجال الهائل من التنوع الحيوي المختفي يزداد أكثر
by the dark matter of the biological world of bacteria,
بالحالة المظلمة لعالم التنوع الحيوي للبكتريا،
which within just the last several years
التي خلال السنوات القليلة الماضية فقط
still were known from only about 6,000 species of bacteria worldwide.
ما تزال غير معروفة من حوالي 6 الآف فقط من مخلوقات البكتريا عالمياً.
But that number of bacteria species can be found in one gram of soil,
لكن هذا العدد من مخلوقات البكتريا يمكن إيجادها في حفنة ضئيلة من التربة،
just a little handful of soil, in the 10 billion bacteria that would be there.
في حفنة يد من التربة، من شأن 10 مليارات باكتيريا أن تكون هناك.
It's been estimated that a single ton of soil -- fertile soil --
لقد تم تقدير أن طن واحد من التربة -- التربة الخصبة--
contains approximately four million species of bacteria, all unknown.
تحتوي تقريباً على أربعة ملايين مخلوق من البكتريا، كلها غير معروفة.
So the question is: what are they all doing?
إذا فالسؤال هو: ماذا يفعلون كلهم؟
The fact is, we don't know.
في الحقيقة، نحن لا نعلم.
We are living on a planet with a lot of activities, with reference to our living environment,
نحن نعيش على كوكب فيه الكثير من الأنشطة، بالرجوع الى بيئة حياتنا،
done by faith and guess alone.
وذلك عن طريق الإيمان والتخمين وحدهما.
Our lives depend upon these creatures.
حياتنا تعتمد على هذه الكائنات.
To take an example close to home: there are over 500 species of bacteria now known --
لنأخذ مثال قريب من البيت: هناك أكثر من 500 مخلوق من الباكتريا معروفة الآن--
friendly bacteria -- living symbiotically in your mouth and throat
باكتريا صديقة -- تعيش عضوياً في فمك وحلقك
probably necessary to your health for holding off pathogenic bacteria.
من المرجح أنها ضرورية لصحتك التخلص من الباكتريا المسببة للأمراض.
At this point I think we have a little impressionistic film
في هذه النقطة أعتقد أن لدينا فيلم إنطباعي صغير
that was made especially for this occasion.
الذي تم إعداده خصيصاً لهذه المناسبة.
And I'd like to show it.
وأرغب في عرضه عليكم.
Assisted in this by Billie Holiday.
مصحوباً مع عطلة بيلي.
(Video)
(فيديو)
And that may be just the beginning!
وتلك ربما تكون البداية فقط!
The viruses, those quasi-organisms among which are the prophages,
الفيروسات، شبه الكائنات الربانية --
the gene weavers that promote the continued evolution in the lives of the bacteria,
ناسجة الجينات التي تعزز تواصل التطور في حياة الباكتريا--
are a virtually unknown frontier of modern biology, a world unto themselves.
هي حدود غير معروفة إفتراضياً في مجال الأحياء الحديث، عالم في حد ذاتها.
What constitutes a viral species is still unresolved,
ما يشكل عالم من الكائنات ما تزال مجهولة،
although they're obviously of enormous importance to us.
على الرغم من انهم من الواضح على قدر كبير من الأهمية بالنسبة لنا.
But this much we can say: the variety of genes on the planet in viruses
ولكن بالنسبة للكثير من هذا يمكننا القول: مجموعة متنوعة من الجينات على الكوكب في الفيروسات
exceeds, or is likely to exceed, that in all of the rest of life combined.
تزيد أو من المرجح أن تزيد على كل بقية الحياة مجتمعة.
Nowadays, in addressing microbial biodiversity,
هذه الأيام، في معالجة التنوع البيولوجي الميكروبي
scientists are like explorers in a rowboat launched onto the Pacific Ocean.
يبدو العلماء مثل المستكشفين في زورق أطلق على المحيط الهادي.
But that is changing rapidly with the aid of new genomic technology.
لكن ذلك يتغير بسرعة بمساعدة تكنلوجيا الجينوم الحديثة.
Already it is possible to sequence the entire genetic code of a bacterium in under four hours.
من الممكن بالفعل سلسلة كل الشفرة الجينية لجرثومة في أقل من أربعة ساعات.
Soon we will be in a position to go forth in the field with sequencers on our backs --
قريباً سنكون في وضع يمكننا الذهاب قدماً في المجال التسلسل مع التعاقب على ظهورنا--
to hunt bacteria in tiny crevices of the habitat's surface
لمطاردة الباكتريا في شقوق صغيرة على سطح الموائل
in the way you go watching for birds with binoculars.
بالطريقة التي تذهب بها لمراقبة الطيور باستخدام المنظار.
What will we find as we map the living world, as, finally, we get this underway seriously?
ما سنجده خلال رسمنا للعالم الحي، كما، نجد في النهاية، على هذا الطريق الجاد؟
As we move past the relatively gigantic mammals, birds, frogs and plants
بينما ننتقل لما قبل الثديات العملاقة، الطيور، الضفادع والنباتات
to the more elusive insects and other small invertebrates and then beyond
الى الحشرات الأكثر مرواغة واللافقاريات الأخرى الصغيرة وما بعدها--
to the countless millions of organisms in the invisible living world
الى الملايين اللانهائية من الكائنات في العالم الحي غير المرئي
enveloped and living within humanity?
المغطى والذي يعيش مع الإنسانية.
Already what were thought to be bacteria for generations
بالفعل ما كنا نعتقد أنه باكتريا لأجيال
have been found to compose, instead, two great domains of microorganisms:
أتضح أنه بدلاً عن ذلك يؤلف مجالين عظيمين للكائنات المجهرية:
true bacteria and one-celled organisms the archaea,
البكتريا الحقيقية وكائنات عتيقة أحادية الخلية،
which are closer than other bacteria to the eukaryota, the group that we belong to.
التي هي أقرب من بقية البكتريا الى النواة، المجموعة التي ننتمي إليها.
Some serious biologists, and I count myself among them,
بعض علماء الأحياء الجادين، وأنا أحسب نفسي ضمنهم،
have begun to wonder that among the enormous and still unknown diversity of microorganisms,
بدأنا في الإستغراب في أن بين التنوع الهائل والغير معروف من الكائنات المجهرية،
one might -- just might -- find aliens among them.
ربما يجد الشخص -- فقط ربما -- نجد أجانب بينهم.
True aliens, stocks that arrived from outer space.
أجانب حقيقيين، مجموعات وصلت من الفضاء الخارجي.
They've had billions of years to do it,
لقد أستغرقوا مليارات السنين لفعل ذلك،
but especially during the earliest period of biological evolution on this planet.
لكن خاصة خلال الفترات الأولى للتطور الإحيائي على هذا الكوكب.
We do know that some bacterial species that have earthly origin
نحن نعرف أن بعض كائنات البكتريا التي لديها أصل في كوكب الأرض
are capable of almost unimaginable extremes of temperature
يمكنها العيش في درجات حرارة شديدة لا يمكن تخيلها
and other harsh changes in environment,
وغيرها من التغييرات القاسية في البيئة.
including hard radiation strong enough and maintained long enough to crack the Pyrex vessels
وتشمل الإشعاعات القاسية بما يكفي والحفاظ طويلاً للقضاء على خلايا بيركس
around the growing population of bacteria.
حول جمهور الباكتريا المتزايد.
There may be a temptation to treat the biosphere holistically
قد يكون هناك إغراء لعلاج المحيط الحيوي تاريخيا
and the species that compose it as a great flux of entities
والأنواع التي يتكون منها كمادة عظيمة متدفقة
hardly worth distinguishing one from the other.
بالكاد تستطيع تمييز واحد من الآخر.
But each of these species, even the tiniest Prochlorococci,
لكن كل من هذه الأنواع، حتى أصغر البروتشلوروكوكو
are masterpieces of evolution.
هي رائعة من روائع التطور.
Each has persisted for thousands to millions of years.
كل منها قد أستمر لآلاف ملايين السنين.
Each is exquisitely adapted to the environment in which it lives,
كل منها قد تكيّف مع البيئة التي يعيش فيها،
interlocked with other species to form ecosystems upon which our own lives depend
متشابك مع بقية الأنواع لتشكيل النظام البيئي الذي تعتمد عليه حياتنا
in ways we have not begun even to imagine.
بطريقة لم نبدأ بعد في تخيلها.
We will destroy these ecosystems and the species composing them
سنقوم بتدمير هذه الأنظمة البيئية وتلك الأنواع التي تؤلفها
at the peril of our own existence --
في خطر على وجودنا نفسه--
and unfortunately we are destroying them with ingenuity and ceaseless energy.
ولسوء الحظ نحن ندمرها ببراعة و نشاط لا يهدأ .
My own epiphany as a conservationist came in 1953, while a Harvard graduate student,
عيد الغطاس خاصتي كمحافظ على البيئة جاء عام 1953، بينما كنت في جامعة هارفارد
searching for rare ants found in the mountain forests of Cuba,
أبحث عن نمل نادر وُجد في غابة جبلية في كوبا.
ants that shine in the sunlight --
نمل يلمع مع أشعة الشمس--
metallic green or metallic blue, according to species, and one species, I discovered, metallic gold.
معدني أزرق أو أخضر ونوع واحد ، أكتشفت، المعدني الذهبي.
I found my magical ants, but only after a tough climb into the mountains
لقد وجدت النمل الساحر خاصتي، لكن بعد تسلق صعب في الجبال
where the last of the native Cuban forests hung on,
حيث تقبع آخر الغابات الكوبية الأصلية،
and were then -- and still are -- being cut back.
وبعد ذلك -- ما يزال -- يتم إجتثاثها.
I realized then that these species
لقد ادركت حينها أن هذه الأنواع
and a large part of the other unique, marvelous animals and plants on that island --
ومجموعة أخرى كبيرة من الحيوانات المتفردة، الرائعة والنباتات على تلك الجزيرة--
and this is true of practically every part of the world --
وهذا حقيقي تحديداً لكل جزء من العالم--
which took millions of years to evolve, are in the process of disappearing forever.
الذي أستغرق ملايين السنين ليتطور، هي في عملية إختفاء الى الأبد.
And so it is everywhere one looks.
ولهذا فانها في كل مكان تنظر إليه.
The human juggernaut is permanently eroding Earth's ancient biosphere by a combination of forces
القوة البشرية الماحقة تعمل بشكل دائم على تآكل محيط الأرض الحيوي القديم بتجميع القوى
that can be summarized by the acronym "HIPPO," the animal hippo.
التي يمكن تلخيصها بالمصطلح "هيبو ،" حيوان فرس البحر.
H is for habitat destruction, including climate change forced by greenhouse gases.
حرف الهاء لتدمير الطبيعة ، وتشمل تغير المناخ القسري الذي تدفعه إنبعاثات الكربون.
I is for the invasive species like the fire ants, the zebra mussels, broom grasses
حرف الآي لإجتياح الكائنات مثل نمل النار، وعضلات الحمار الوحشي، وأعشاب الوزال
and pathogenic bacteria and viruses that are flooding every country, and at an exponential rate -- that's the I.
البكتيريا المسببة للأمراض والفيروسات التي تملأ كل بلد بمعدل هائل-- ذلك هو حرف الآي.
The P, the first one in "HIPPO," is for pollution.
وحرف البي، الأول في "هيبو،" تمثل التلوث.
The second is for continued population, human population expansion.
والثاني يمثل التزايد السكاني المضطرد.
And the final letter is O, for over-harvesting --
والحرف الأخير هو "أو"، يمثل الحصاد الأبدي--
driving species into extinction by excessive hunting and fishing.
يقود الأنواع الى الإنقراض جراء الصيد المفرط
The HIPPO juggernaut we have created, if unabated, is destined --
الهيبو الماحق الذي صنعناه، إذا لم يتوقف، فأنه سيتجه--
according to the best estimates of ongoing biodiversity research --
وفقاً لأفضل تقديرات لبحوث التنوع الحيوي الجارية--
to reduce half of Earth's still surviving animal and plant species
سيقلل نصف الحيوانات التي ما تزال حية وأنواع النباتات
to extinction or critical endangerment by the end of the century.
سيعرضها للإنقراض أو الخطر الحرج بنهاية هذا القرن.
Human-forced climate change alone -- again, if unabated --
تغير المناخ بسبب البشر وحده -- مجدداً، إن لم يتوقف --
could eliminate a quarter of surviving species during the next five decades.
قد يقلل ربع الأنواع الحية خلال العقود الخمس القادمة
What will we and all future generations lose
ما سنفقده نحن وبقية أجيال المستقبل
if much of the living environment is thus degraded?
إذا تم تدمير الكثير من البيئة الحية ؟
Huge potential sources of scientific information yet to be gathered,
قابلية مصادر ضخمة للمعلومات العلمية التي لم يتم تجميعها بعد،
much of our environmental stability
الكثير من إستقرارنا البيئي
and new kinds of pharmaceuticals and new products of unimaginable strength and value --
وأنواع جديدة من العقاقير الطبية ومنتجات جديدة لقوى لا يمكن تخيلها وقيمة --
all thrown away.
كلها ستُلقى عرضاً.
The loss will inflict a heavy price
الخسارة ستلحق ثمناً باهظاً
in wealth, security and yes, spirituality for all time to come,
في الثروة، الأمن ونعم، وللقيم الروحية لكل الأزمان القادمة.
because previous cataclysms of this kind --
لأن الكوارث السابقة من هذا النوع--
the last one, that ended the age of dinosaurs --
آخر واحدة قضت على عهد الديناصورات--
took, normally, five to 10 million years to repair.
أخذت، طبيعياً، خمس الى عشرة ملايين سنة ليتم إصلاحها.
Sadly, our knowledge of biodiversity is so incomplete
للأسف، معرفتنا بالتنوع الحيوي غير مكتملة بشدة
that we are at risk of losing a great deal of it before it is even discovered.
بحيث أننا نخاطر بفقدان قدر كبير منها حتى قبل إكتشافها.
For example, even in the United States, the 200,000 species known currently
على سبيل المثال، حتى في الولايات المتحدة، فان 200 ألف نوع المعروفة حالياً
actually has been found to be only partial in coverage;
في الواقع تم إكتشافها لتصبح جزئياً مغطاة.
it is mostly unknown to us in basic biology.
وأنها في الغالب غير معروفة لنا في الأحياء الأساسية.
Only about 15 percent of the known species have been studied well enough to evaluate their status.
فقط حوالي 15 في المائة من الأنواع المعروفة تم دراستها بما يكفي لتقييم حالتها.
Of the 15 percent evaluated, 20 percent are classified as "in peril,"
من ال 15 في المائة التي تم تقييمها، تم تصنيف 20 في المائة منها على أنها "في خطر."
that is, in danger of extinction.
ذلك هو، في خطر الإنقراض.
That's in the United States.
ذلك في الولايات المتحدة.
We are, in short, flying blind into our environmental future.
نحن، باختصار، نطير كالعميان في مستقبل بيئتنا.
We urgently need to change this.
نحن نحتاج لتغيير هذا بسرعة طارئة.
We need to have the biosphere properly explored
نحتاج لأن نستكشف الغلاف الجوي بصورة صحيحة
so that we can understand and competently manage it.
بحيث يمكننا فهمه وتنظيمه بالكامل.
We need to settle down before we wreck the planet.
نحتاج لأن نستقر قبل أن ندمّر الكوكب.
And we need that knowledge.
ونحتاج لتلك المعرفة.
This should be a big science project equivalent to the Human Genome Project.
وينبغي أن يكون هذا مشروع علمي كبير مكافئ لمشروع الجينوم البشري.
It should be thought of as a biological moonshot with a timetable.
ويجب التفكير فيه كصورة بيولوجية للقمر مع جدول زمني.
So this brings me to my wish for TEDsters,
إذاً هذا يوصلني لأمنيتي لزملائي في تيد،
and to anyone else around the world who hears this talk.
ولأي شخص آخر حول العالم يستمع لهذا الحديث.
I wish we will work together to help create the key tools
أتمنى أن نعمل سوياً للمساعدة في صنع الأدوات المناسبة
that we need to inspire preservation of Earth's biodiversity.
التي نحتاجها للحفاظ على التنوع الحيوي في الأرض.
And let us call it the "Encyclopedia of Life."
ودعونا نطلق عليها " موسوعة الحياة."
What is the "Encyclopedia of Life?" A concept that has already taken hold
ما هي "موسوعة الحياة"-- مفهوم أتخذ بالفعل
and is beginning to spread and be looked at seriously?
وهو في بداية الإنتشار والنظر إليه بجدية؟
It is an encyclopedia that lives on the Internet
إنها موسوعة تعيش على الإنترنت
and is contributed to by thousands of scientists around the world.
وهي مساهمة من آلالاف العلماء حول العالم.
Amateurs can do it also.
يستطيع الهواة فعلها أيضاً.
It has an indefinitely expandable page for each species.
انها صفحة قابلة للتوسيع إلى أجل غير مسمى لكل الأنواع.
It makes all key information about life on Earth accessible to anyone,
إنها تصنع المعلومات الأساسية حول الحياة على الأرض وجعلها متاحة للجميع،
on demand, anywhere in the world.
عند الطلب، في أي مكان في العالم.
I've written about this idea before,
لقد كتبت عن هذه الفكرة في السابق،
and I know there are people in this room who have expended significant effort on it in the past.
واعرف أن هناك أشخاص في هذه القاعة الذين بذلوا جهوداً مقدرة فيها في السابق.
But what excites me is that since I first put forward this particular idea in that form,
لكن ما أذهلني هو أنه منذ أن وضعت هذه الفكرة تحديداً في ذلك الشكل قدماً،
science has advanced.
لقد تقدم العلم.
Technology has moved forward.
لقد تقدمت التكنلوجيا الى الأمام.
Today, the practicalities of making such an encyclopedia,
اليوم، الجوانب العلمية لإنشاء مثل هذه الموسوعة،
regardless of the magnitude of the information put into it, are within reach.
غض النظر عن حجم المعلومات الموضوعة فيها، هي في متناول اليد.
Indeed, in the past year, a group of influential scientific institutions
بالطبع، في السنة الماضية مجموعة من المؤسسات العلمية المؤثرة
have begun mobilizing to realize this dream.
بدأت في الترويج لها لتحقيق هذا الحلم.
I wish you would help them.
أتمنى أن أستطيع مساعدتهم.
Working together, we can make this real.
بالعمل سوياً، يمكننا جعل ذلك حقيقة.
The encyclopedia will quickly pay for itself in practical applications.
الموسوعة ستقوم بالصرف على نفسها بسرعة في تطبيقات عملية.
It will address transcendent qualities in the human consciousness, and sense of human need.
ستقوم بمخاطبة الوعي العالي للإنسان، والشعور بالحوجة البشرية.
It will transform the science of biology in ways of obvious benefit to humanity.
ستقوم بتحول علم الأحياء بطرق واضحة لمصلحة البشرية.
And most of all, it can inspire a new generation of biologists
والأهم من ذلك كله، يمكنها أن تلهم الجيل الجديد من علماء الأحياء
to continue the quest that started, for me personally, 60 years ago:
للمواصلة في السعي الذي بدأ، بالنسبة لي شخصياً، قبل 60 عاماً:
to search for life, to understand it and finally, above all, to preserve it.
للبحث عن حياة، لفهمها وفي النهاية -- فوق كل هذا -- للحفاظ عليها.
That is my wish. Thank you.
تلك هي أمنيتي. شكراً لكم.